Three, two, one, go! He
three two one
had unknowingly wandered right up to
go had unknowingly wanded right up to
the front line. The first gunshot
the front line the first gunshot
signaled the beginning of another day's
signaled the beginning of another day's
Mayhem, an unforgettable ordeal with gangs. Over the next few days,
Mayhem a roue uncforblyiliar with over
Kid r the city, so sold
the next days gangs Kid r the city so
of the
sold of the
[Music]
[Musique]
variousb human
variousb human
I'm contacting you
ieur bonjour Je vous intervie
today for a YouTube channel
aujourd'hui pour une chaîne Youtube qui
called [Music]. I would like to ask a
s'appellew j'aurais voulu avoir des
few questions about your latest film
petites réponses sur votre dernier film
concerning chemical weapons. What is the name of the
concernant les armes chimiques comment
film? It's called "
s'appelle-t-il film s'appelle arm
Chemical Weapons Under the Sea," and how long ago did you make it? We made it
chimique sous la mer et vous l'avez
last year. It was
réalisé l'année dernière il a été
broadcast on the Art channel in
diffusé sur la chaîne art en février en
February 2014. So this film deals with
février 2014 donc ce film traite de des
global arsenals buried under the sea,
arsenaux mondiaux en fouie sous la mer
in lakes all over Europe.
dans les lacs un peu partout en Europe
What was the most polluted place
quel était l'endroit le plus pollué que
you were able to visit? Actually, it's
vous avez pu visiter en fait le c'est
mainly the chemical weapons that were...
surtout les les armes chiques qui ont
I was in the oceans, in the
été J était dans les océans dans les
seas, in all the oceans of the world, and
mers dans toutes les océans du monde et
we filmed all over the world. TR
on a filmé partout dans le monde TR
four  continents, and we can say that the
quatre continents et on peut dire que
most polluted ocean or sea
l'océan ou les mer la plus polluée
was undoubtedly the Baltic. Polluted
c'était la Baltique sans doute pollu
with what? In the Baltic, it was
avec quoi dans la Baltique c'était
mainly mustard gas, which is called
surtout la gaz moutarde qu'on appelle le
in French "hit," I think it's called "hperit." So,
en français le hit je crois hperit voilà
what is the risk, in fact, of this
et quel est le risque en fait de cette
burial under the sea?
cet enfuissement sous la mer
What are the risks? The
euh quels sont les risques c'est surtout
risks are mainly for the fishermen, for
les risques sont pour les pêcheurs pour
the fish, and for
les pour les poissons et pour
the
l'environnement
marine environment. All the organizations
euh de la mer tous les organismes qui
there, the researchers you were able to
sont là les les chercheurs que vous avez
meet who were investigating this
pu rencontrer qui enquêtaient sur ce
subject, gave you a deadline, a
sujet-là euh vous ont donné un délai un
critical time. The problem is that
temps critique euh le problème c'est que
most of these weapons were dumped
la plupart de ces armes ont été jettées
after the Second World War. There are
après la seconde guerre mondial il y a
weapons that were dumped before that,
des des armes qui ont été jeté avant ça
for the First World War, but
pour la première guerre mondiale mais la
most were dumped after the Second
plupart on été jeté après la Seconde
World War, and they were dumped
Guerre mondiale et ils ont été jetés
in... French barrels, those are
dans des euh français que c'est Barel
metal barrels,
c'est barils des barils en métal
and these barrels have a lifespan
et ces barils ont une vie à cause de la
of more or less
corrosion la corrosion de plus ou moins
50 years due to corrosion. That is to say, we...  We are
50 ans c'est-à-dire que nous sommes
now reaching a
maintenant on arrive à la période
pivotal moment, this is the
charnière voilà c'est c'est le moment
critical moment where these weapons are being deployed. The
critique où ces armes
barriers are being
vont barelles sont en train de de
opened and these chemical weapons are being deployed. Have
s'ouvrir et ses armes chimiques sont en
you investigated a
train de est-ce que vous avez enquêté un
little bit about the English Channel, the
petit peu sur la Manche sur la mer
Mediterranean Sea, the French Riviera? Yes,
Méditerranée la Côte d'Azur oui euh
especially here in France,
surtout il y a même ici en France il y a
on the French Riviera, there are areas where even
sur la Côte d'Azur il y a des zones même
today we see signs where we ca
aujourd'hui on voit des signes où on
n't swim, but we don't know
peut pas se baigner mais on ne sait pas
why. It's because of chemical
pourquoi il mais c'est à cause de des
weapons that have been dumped there. And
armeschées qui ont été jetés là et
especially, we haven't filmed in France,
surtout on a on a pas filmé en France
but we've filmed a lot in Italy, the
mais on a filmé beaucoup en Italie la
Adriatic coast, which is really another
côte adriatique qui a vraiment une autre
coast that is very, very polluted. After the
côte qui est très très pollu après la
Baltic, we can say that Italy
Baltique on peut dire que c'est l'Italie
itself has a lot of chemical weapons
même qui a beaucoup euh des AB qui se
in the Adriatic Ocean. Have you
trouve dans l'océan Adriatique vous avez
met with the population? Have you
rencontré la population est-ce que vous
discussed
vous avez discuté de la avec la
the risk they face with the population?
population du risque qu'il
Most of the
encourrait la plupart de la la
population isn't aware of this
population ne sont pas au courant de ce
problem because it's a sensitive subject.  It's very, very
problème parce que c'est un sujet très
secret, nobody's been talking about
très secécré qui a été personne n parlé
it, and really, we can say that this
de ça et vraiment on peut dire que ce
film is the first time it's been
film c'est la première fois que
discussed publicly. There have been
discuté dans publiquement il y a eu des
investigations done by
enquêtes qui ont été fait par des
journalists, especially in Italy. One
journalistes surtout en Italie un
journalist wrote a book about it, I don't know
journaliste qui acé un livre il y a
how many years ago, but it was quite
je sais pas combien d'années mais c'est
recently, about five years ago. But it's
assez récemment il y a 5 ans mais c'est
a new subject. And when
c'est un nouveau sujet et quand à part
we talked to people we
ça qu' on a parlé avec des personnes
were filming by the
qu'on était en train de filmer au bord
sea, either on the Baltic Sea or
de la mer soit de la Baltique ou
in Italy, and we met
soit en Italie et on rencontrait des
people, they asked us what
gens et on nous demandait qu'est-ce que
we were doing, asked them if
vous faites on leur demandait est-ce que
they knew there were chemical weapons.
vous savez qu'il y a des armes chimiques
Everyone was very shocked. I think
tout le monde était très choqué je pense
the population isn't aware,
que la population ne sont pas au courant
and it's a subject that frightens many people.
et c'est un sujet qui effraye beaucoup
You were chosen to be the
vous avez été choisi pour être le
director of this
réalisateur les réalisateur de ce
documentary because you were
documentaire parce que vous étiez à la
also the director of a film called "
base aussi réalisateur d'un film qui
Entraxoir."
s'appelle entraxoir est-ce que vous
Can you tell us a little about that film? Yes,
pouvez nous dire deux mots sur ce film
the film is...
là oui le film
A film that reflects the current state of
in c'est un film qui r à la situation de
biological
sybiologique en ce moment les les
research, the
recherches qui se
ongoing development of biological agents,
passent développement des es biologiques
and really, it's a film that started
et vraiment c'est un film qui a démarré
after the Crax attacks, or just
après les attaques de d'rax ou juste
after 9/11 in the United States.
après le 11 septembre aux États-Unis des
Letters containing Crax's information were
lettres qui contenaient derax ont été
sent to media outlets and
envoyé à des des médias et à des
some American senators in
quelques sénateurs américains à
Washington. And you investigated
Washington et et vous avez enquêé sur
the strains of this DNA? Yes, we investigated. It was one of the
les souches de cette anentrax oui on on
things
a enqué c'était une des une des choses
we did in this film: to
qu'on a fait dans ce film c'est de
look at Crax's DNA to
regarder le sou de Crax pour
find out where it came from and to conduct a
savoirù ça venait et de de faire une
forensic investigation.
investigation qui était forensique en
So, what
comment dit et donc qu'est-ce que vous
did you highlight about this strain?
avez mis en avant sur C souche
If we look at this strain, it's what we
là si on regarde cette souche c'est une
called a
appellelais uneche
weaponized strain, and it was very
militarisé euh et qui était très très
sophisticated, developed with a
sophistiqué qui a été travaillé
lot of resources. The conclusion, in
beaucoup de moyens et la conclusion en
fact, was that it was
fait euh que
a strain that was really sophisticated, that it
c'était une souche qui était vraiment
must have come from a
travaillée que c'est ça devait venir
state project.  It's impossible that a
d'État que c'était pas possible que une
person,
personne
or even a small group of people,
ou même un petit groupe de personnes
could develop such a strain. These are very, very
puissent développer une souche pareille
powerful means. In your opinion, do
sont des grands grands moyens votre avis
you think this was a
est-ce que vous pensez que c'était une
way for the state to intimidate
façon dont l'État avait d'intimider
certain institutions to legitimize
certaines institutions pour légitimer
some
quelques lois
anti-terrorism laws in the face of the spread
antiterroristes face à la propagation
of biological weapons? We can't
d'armes biologiques on ne peut pas
know the reasons, in fact, but we ca
savoir les les raisons en fait mais on
n't really speculate. But
peut pas spéculer vraiment mais mais
it's certain that what
c'est sûr que
happened, that
euh ce qui est arrivé que
these attacks,
ces attaques ont
launched a lot of new
lancé une beaucoup de nouveaux
research on biological weapons and a
recherches sur les es biologiques et
lot of very, very large expenditures
beaucoup de très très grandes dépenses
and budgets that were allocated to
et des grands budgets qui ont été fait
it. But we also know that
sur ça mais on sait vraiment que aussi
biological weapons aren't talked about
que les armes biologiques on en parle
much, but that all states
pas beaucoup mais que tous les États
are working on
sont en train de travailler sur
it. You're a war reporter; you covered
çaen vous êtes reporterur de guerre vous
some conflicts, like Moravia in the
certains conflits comme morovia à la
Belle Époque. What
belle époque euh qu'est-ce qui vous a
determined you, or what
déterminé ou qu'est-ce qui vous a
predestined you, to investigate this type of
prédestiné à enquêter sur ce type de
biological weapons scandal? For me, it came from growing up
biologique pour moi ça venait de j'ai
in Africa, in Zimbabwe.
grandi en Afrique euh zimbab au Zimbabwe
At the time, Zimbabwe was a British colony.  In
à l'époque c'était la colonie anglaise
Rhodesia, we experienced a
la rodisie nous avons vécu une guerre
very violent war of independence, and I grew up
très violente d'indépendance et moi j'ai
in
grandi dans la société
Colon society. I was a young peasant, like any other peasant,
de Colon j'étais un petit col comme un
and when I reached adulthood,
petit colon et quand je j'ai attenu
the war was raging.
l'âge l'âge majeur la guerre était en
Many of my school friends went to fight, but I didn't. I ran away.
pleine force là et beaucoup de mes amis
But later, after I became a
suis enfu mais après que je suis devenu
journalist, I learned that the Rwandan forces,
journaliste j'ai su que les forces
the government army,
armées l'armée du gouvernement
used biological and chemical weapons,
a utilisé les armes euh biologiques et
and especially
les armes euh chimiques euh et surtout
anthrax.
ils ont utilisé l'anthrax on peut dire
Zimbabwe had the largest
que le zimbabweé a eu la plus grande
anthrax epidemic in
épidémie d'anthrax dans l'année
1998, which killed over 300
1998 euh qui a tué euh plus de 300
people and infected over 10,000. And then, in
personnes et infecté plus de 10000
2001, I found myself in New York, right at
après en en 2001 à New York juste à
the time of the anthrax outbreak, and I wondered if there was
l'époque de l'attaque d' Antrax et je me
a connection.
suis demandé est-ce qu'il y a un lien
Between what happened in my country
entre ce qui s'est passé dans mon pays
of Zimbabwe and what happened in the United States,
de zimbabweé et ce qui s'est passéit aux
and that's what started the
États-Unis et c'est ça qui a démarré le
film, it's about the consequences of this type of
film c'estour de conséquen ce type de
reasoning. Yeah, it was a question,
raisonnement ouais c'était une question
it was interesting to see if there's
c'était intéressé pour voir est-ce que
a link. Last
il y a un lien est-ce que dernière
question for you, Bob, uh,
question pour vous Bob
what is the worst conflict
euh quel est le le le pire conflit que
you've had to witness during your
vous avez été amené à voir durant votre
career as a
carrière de reporteur de
war reporter? All conflicts are bad,
guerre tous les les conflits
terrible.
sont sont mauvais sont terribles la
War is something awful to
guerre c'est quelque chose de d'affreux
experience, but we can say
expériencer mais on peut dire
perhaps Ivea was
peut-être l'ivéia c'était
particularly, we can say a bit crazy
particulièrement on peut dire un peu fou
because it was young men,
à cause que céit des jeunes hommes qui
young people who were drugged with
étai des jeunes gens qui étaient drogués
drugs, a lot of confusion, a lot of
Ares beaucoup de confusions beaucoup de
disorder, and a lot of danger.
désordres et beaucoup de dangers
Introduce us to your friend. So, I'll
présentez-nous votre Amic alors je vous
introduce you to my partner, Eric Nadla. We
présente mon mon associé Eric nadla on a
worked together on two
on a travaillé ensemble sur les deux
films:
films les armes
Chemical Weapons Under the Sea and our film
chimiques sous la mer et notre film
Atrax War, which we also made together. And
atrax war qu'on a fait ensemble aussi et
that makes  10 years we work
ça fait 10 ans que nous travaons
enssazscentary 2
enssazscentary 2
years what Drew me to this to is had
years what Drew me to this to is had
interest for many years in weapons of
interest for many years in weapons of
mass destruction
mass destruction
whicht with the nuclear weapons
whicht with the nuclear weapons
underground and we had exclusive access
underground and we had exclusive access
to the first man accused of nuclear
to the first man accused of nuclear
espionage since Klaus fuk back in the
espionage since Klaus fuk back in the
50s he was a German um he had access to
50s he was a German um he had access to
uranium enrichment technology um uh for
uranium enrichment technology um uh for
a firm where he worked and he took those
a firm where he worked and he took those
plans and he sold them to um Iraqi
plans and he sold them to um Iraqi
agents for Saddam Hussein and there was
agents for Saddam Hussein and there was
a worldwide Manhunt on for him after
a worldwide Manhunt on for him after
those plans were found in a chicken
those plans were found in a chicken
coop uh that the United Nations
cooup uh that the United Nations
inspectors were sent to by uh uh
inspectors were sent to by uh uh
Hussein's uh brother-in-law and uh as
Hussein's uh brother-inlaw and uh as
soon as they saw the plans they knew
soon as they saw the plans they knew
that this man carlheim SH had taken them
that this man carlheim SH had taken them
and he was hiding in Brazil and uhuse he
and he was hiding in Brazil and uhuse he
didn't think thered be an extradition
didn't think thered be an extradition
Treaty he also was helping Brazilians
Treaty he also was helping Brazilians
with their secret nuclear program
with their secret nuclear program
helping them to Devel a nuclear
helping them to Devel a nuclear
submarine among other things but
submarine among other things but
eventually the Brazilians  extradited
eventually the Brazilians extradited
into Germany he stood trial he was
into Germany he stood trial he was
accused  of treason and nuclear espionage
accused of treason and nuclear espionage
he was found guilty and he was find
he was found guilty and he was find
32,000 EUR and given a suspended
32,000 EUR and given a suspended
sentence he's a free man today and um
sentence he's a free man today and um
this was my first film on weapons of
this was my first film on weapons of
mass destruction and then uh Bob and I
mass destruction and then uh Bob and I
got together
got together
bi we and weic we all ones and may
bi we and weic we all ones and may
that's us now I don't know ok I would
that's us now I don't know ok I would
point of view about the war in Iraq so
point of view about the war in Iraq so
they talk about we of M
they talk about we of M
destruction arsenal of SAM was he and
destruction arsenal of SAM was he and
legitimize the war this
legitimat the war this
pr point of
pr point of
is at  some in the 190s he had a nuclear
is at some in the 190s he had a nuclear
program as many countries do
program as many countries do
it and there was no real information
it and there was no real information
that he
that he
had revived it again um he certainly had
had revived it again um he certainly had
the software the plans to that he obtain
the software the plans to that he obtain
from SH for uranium technology very very
from SH for uranium technology very very
very sophisticated stuff once he had
very sophisticated stuff once he had
that who knows what he could do with it
that who knows what he could do with it
could sell it whatever but the pretext
could sell it whatever but the pretext
that he had biological weapons that he
that he had biological weapons that he
had nuclear weapons um was uh never
had nuclear weapons um was uh never
proven so the basic justification uh for
proven so the basic justification uh for
that War I think was an illegitimate one
that War I think was an illegitimate one
ultimately i think they cooked the books
ultimately i think they cooked the books
the  Americans cooked the books skewed
the Americans cooked the books skewed
the data linked  it to the media created
the data linked it to the media created
a frenzy and uh to this day they haven't
a frenzy and uh to this day they haven't
found any proof that his program
found any proof that his program
continued in a sophisticated manner uh
continued in a sophisticated manner uh
despite some moves back in the 90s in
despite some moves back in the 90s in
fact
fact
maradfi had a sophisticated program as
maradfi had a sophisticated program as
well he gave up the program um and uh
well he gave up the program um and uh
was one of the few countries to actually
was one of the few countries to actually
give up program I don't know if that was
give up program I don't know if that was
wise or not cuuse they eventually uh
wise or not cuuse they eventually uh
ousted him and killed him um and so I
ousted him and killed him um and so I
don't know what sign that sends to the M
don't know what sign that sends to the M
and Iran what  you do with your weapons
and Iran what you do with your weapons
but as far as the Iraq war goes i think
but as far as the Iraq war goes i think
it was illegitimate and I think it was
it was illegitimate and I think it was
done
done
some sort of revenge for 9 but nothing
some sort of revenge for 9 but nothing
to do with 9 so I think it's been a
to do with 9 so I think it's been a
tragedy for the region and the
tragedy for the region and the
world what was your your reaction when
world what was your your reaction when
you saw Colin po with a little bit of fr
you saw Colin po with a little bit of fr
who SH down tracks in front of a lot of
who SH down tracks in front of a lot of
diplomatic persons well this is before I
diplomatic persons well this is before I
did serious research into this topic
done serious research into this topic
for the film this is when I was just an
for the film this is when I was just an
American citizen and I was alarmed in
American citizen and I was alarmed in
other words
other words
if the American  intelligence people had
if the American intelligence people had
convinced Colin Pow  Who was kind of a
convinced Colin Pow who was kind of a
career soldier, not a real spooky guy, to
career soldier not a real spooky Guy to
stand up in front of the world and say
stand up in front of the world and say
that he was producing this? Well, I was
that he was producing this well I was I
concerned, but as we know now, the
was concerned but as we know now the the
evidence wasn't there, and the speech he gave
evidence was not there and the speech he
was false. So, in retrospect,
gave was false and so uh in retrospect
I'm angry about that. But at the
I'm angry about that and uh but at the
time, I viewed it like most citizens and
time I viewed it like most citizens and
was like that.
was comme ça
Bob, when you saw Colin Powell
Bob quand vous avez vu Colin Powell
waving a little anthrax, what was
agiter un peu d'antrax quelle était quel
your reaction at the time, and
a été votre réaction à l'époque et
what is your reaction now?
quelle est maintenant votre réaction
It was a very, very important point
c'était un point très très important
for everyone who went into the war. Yes,
pour tout qui a été rentr en guerre oui
going into the war was
la rentrée en guerre c'était c'était
very important, and in our film, a
très important et dans notre film un
war, it's also a very important point
war c'est aussi un point très important
because,
parce
through researching history, what happened
que à travers de chercher l'histoire
in the
qu'est-ce qui s'est passait dans les es
biological fields? We were also concerned about the
biologiques aussi on a inquiété sur les
deaths of researchers, several
morts de des chercheurs plusieurs
researchers, and the most famous was
chercheurs et le plus fameux c'était
David Kelly, who was the one who
David Kelly qui était celui qui
said, because when Colin Powell
avait dit parce que quand col Paul a
took this anthrax, it was based on
pris cette cet untrax c'était sur des
intelligence they received from
renseignement qu'ils ont eu à travers
the British, the Americans, and  In fact,
les Anglais les Américains et en fait
David Kelly spoke out against it and
euh David Kelly avait parlé contre ça et
said that the dossier had been fabricated, meaning
qui avait dit que que le dossier a été
fabricated.
sexta ça veut dire fabriqué
And it's because of this that the BBC had
et et c'est à cause de ça que la BBC en
a huge scandal because
fait il a eu un grand scandale parce que
he said
il avait dit
it
ça
unofficially. But at the time, the BBC
unoficially mais la BBC à l'époque on a
gave his name; they said it was him who
donné son nom on l'a dit c'est lui qui
had said it, and it caused a very, very
avait dit ça et ça a provoqué un très
big scandal in England
très grand scandale euh en Angleterre
that
qui a
almost forced Tron Holstein to resign
presque forcé Tron HBL à démissionner à
because of it. And it actually
cause à cause de ça et qui en fait a a
caused David Kelly's death in one way or another.
causé la mort d'une façon et d'une autre
It was said that he committed
de de David Kelly on a dit qu'il s'est
suicide a few days after he
suicidé euh quelques jours après que il
appeared before the British Parliament to
a été devant le Parlement anglais pour
answer questions on the subject. It was a
répondre à des questions sur le sujet
very suspicious suicide in many
suicide très suspect dans beaucoup de
ways, but it was
choses et mais
undoubtedly a very, very
alors sans doute euh c'était un moment
important moment for the
très très important pour euh pour les
major powers to enter Iraq.
grandes puissances pour rentrer en Irak
And as we know now,
et et comme nous le savons maintenant 11
9/11, Iraq—we are still living with the
septembre l'Irak nous vivons les
consequences today.
conséquences jusqu'àaujourd'hui
I'm going to ask you both one last question.
je vais vous poser une dernière question
then a penultimate
à vous deux puis une avantdernière
question sorry and then a last
question pardon et puis une dernière
question we are lucky to have
question nous avons la chance d'avoir de
Americans in front of the camera I
américains en face de la caméra je
would like to have your perception on the
voudrais avoir votre perception sur le
concept of war against terrorism
concept de guerre contre le terrorisme
terror it's hard to understand what
terror it's hard to understand what
groups are out there who's doing who's
groups are out there who's doing who's
behind it who benefits from the chaos
behind it who benefits from the chaos
that this war on terror causes um I know
that this war on terror causes um I know
a few things that have been done in the
a few things that have been done in the
name of the war on terror that uh
name of the war on terror that uh
frighten me as a citizen uh basically in
frighten me as a citizen uh basically in
terms of the United States the passing
terms of the United States the passing
of the Patriot Act civil  liberties are
of the Patriot Act civil liberties are
threatened in fact in the recent
threatened in fact in the recent
Revelations ofward Snowden we see that
Revelations ofward Snowden we see that
national security state is an
national security state is an
international surveillance state gege
international surveillance state gege
Orwell 1984 has come in the of the war
Orwell 1984 has come in the of the war
on terror
on terror
um it raises the question whether safety
um it raises the question whether safety
or Liberty or
or Liberty or
freedom can be Tred off in a way that
freedom can be Tred off in a way that
benefits many citizens so I think a lot
benefits many citizens so I think a lot
is done by the State in terms of the war
is done by the State in terms of the war
on terror that goes beyond things they've ever
on terror that goes beyond things theyve
done before and you go to the roots
ever done before and you go to the roots
of who's actually the terrorist out
of who's actually the terrorist out
there a few i don't  know
there a few i don't know
h people a handful of people are causing
h people a handful of people are causing
these problems and  Uh, the films we're
these problems and uh the films we're
doing lately look into these shadowy
doing lately look into these shadowy
wars. We're really not sure who the
Wars we're really not sure who the
players are, who they're working for, so
players are who they're working for so
it raises a lot of questions. The war on
it raises a lot of questions the war on
terror makes me uneasy because if
terror makes me uneasy a because if
there are two terrors doing terrible
there are two terror doing terrible
things, that's a horrible thing, but if
things that's horrible thing but if
some governments are manipulating the
someh governments are manipulating the
situation to increase their power, that's
situation to increase their powers
also troubling. So I'm really
that's also troueling so I'm really
troubled by the entire scenario of the
troubled by the entire scenario of the
post-9/11 world. Uh, I live in New York City. Uh,
post 91 World uh i live in New York City
I edited a film. Uh, downtown Manhattan, every night I looked out and I
um i edited a film uh downtown Manhattan
saw the shining
every night I looked out and I saw the
R, the World Trade Center, and the
sming R the world trade center and the
world that my children grew up in.
world that my childrenw up in
[Music]
[Musique]
Your perception of the war on
votre perception de la guerre contre le
terror is, we can say it's a
terrorisme c'est on peut dire c'est une
war of... There are many things we don't
guerre de l' il y a beaucoup de choses
know,
qu' qu' ne sait pas
and we have to ask ourselves, what does
et on doit se demander qu'est-ce que ça
terrorism mean? Also, I
veut dire le terrorisme aussi j'ai
grew up in Africa, and during the war of
grandi aussi en Afrique et la guerre de
liberation, we were told when I was growing up that it was
libération on nous a dit quand j'ai
terrorists too.
grandi que c'était des terroristes aussi
And who are the real terrorists? What are...
et qui sont les vrais terroristes
It's about terrorism,
qu'est-ce que c'est que le terrorisme en
but we also have to look at the fact that
fait mais aussi on doit regarder que
after the Cold War, we
après la guerre froide euh que on avait
needed—and still need—a
besoin on a toujours besoin d'un d'un
villain, an enemy,
méchant d'un ennemi d'un ennemi de
someone to be afraid of, first of all to
quelqu'un d'avoir peur euh et pour
control people. But above all, there's
d'abord contrôler les gens mais surtout
the economic aspect:
aussi il y a l'aspect économique que des
immense spending, huge
des dépenses immenses
budgets, the
des budgets la
militarization of the
militarisation des
armed forces under the name of the war on
armées sous le nom de la guerre contre
terror. So there are many,
le terrorisme alors il y a beaucoup
many questions we ask ourselves,
beaucoup de questions qu'on se pose
and we can really say that
et et ça vraiment on peut dire que
since the war on
depuis que la guerre contre le
terror began after
terrorisme va commencer après le 11
9/11, the world has
septembre vraiment le monde a changé
completely changed. Last question: [
complètement dernière question
Music]
[Musique]
Question: Authority, as always, I tell you, don't believe what
question authority as always i tell my
you read in the
don't believe what you read in the
papers, don't believe what your government says. Think for yourself, and basically,
papers don't believe what your
organize around issues that are important
um organize around issues that
to you. I think the hold of
areimportant to you I think the hold of
power, at least in the United
the powers that be at least in United
States, I think basically the government
States i think basically the government
is run by a military-industrial complex
is run by a military industrial complex
that supersedes Republicans or Democrats who have
that superseds Republicans or Democrats
come to believe that war is a
that has come to believe that war um is
very profitable venture. We're living  In
very profitable venture we're living in
a time of eternal war, and basically I
a time of eternal war and basically I
think you have to make the government
think you have to uh make the government
accountable for all its claims, so
accountable uh for all its claims so
basically question authority and don't
basically question authority and do not
be afraid to engage in civil
be afraid uh to engage in civil
disobedience when you don't believe
disobedience when you don't believe uh
[Music].
[Musique]
It's really the same thing. I think
c'est vraiment la même chose je pense
we should always not accept what we're told,
que on doit toujours ne pas accepter ce
ask
qu'on ce qu'on nous dit de de demander
questions, not trust what we're told, what we
des questions de ne pas faire confiance
read, what we
à ce qu'on nous dit de ce qu'on lit ce
see on television. But I think
qu'on voit à la télévision mais je pense
young people already know this. I
que les jeunes ils savent ça déjà je
think this generation is already
pense que la génération sont déjà
aware of this and shouldn't be afraid to educate themselves, to
saperçoit de ça et de ne pas avoir peur
try to find
aussi de ne pas de s'éduquer d'essayer
answers, to ask
de de chercher des réponses de demander
questions, and above all, not be
des questions et surtout de ne pas avoir
afraid. We shouldn't be afraid; we must
peur que on doit pas avoir pe on doit
have
avoir du
courage. And it's really up to them to
courage et c'est vraiment à eux à
change. We are our
changer nous sommes notre
generation; we have caused many
génération on a causé beaucoup de
problems, but we will leave many
problèmes mais on va laisser beaucoup de
problems for the young people, and it's
problèmes pour pour les jeunes et c'est
really up to them, it's in their hands, to
vraiment à eux c'est dans leur main de
change, to use the technology they have.  In a
de changer aussi de d'utiliser la tech
smart way, because technology, the
intelligente parce que la technologie
internet, and all the information they
l'Internet et tout l'information qu'ils
have at their fingertips can be
ont au bout de doigt ça peut être
used negatively for
utilisé d'une façon négative pour le
control, as we've seen, but it
contrôle qu' qu'on l'a vu mais aussi ça
can also
peut
be used very, very
être utilisé d'une façon très très
powerfully to change, to spread a wave of
puissante pour changer propager une épie
good, an epidemic of good, thanks
du bien grâce une épidémie du bien grâce
to technology. That's exactly it.
à technologie voà c'est ça exactement
Thank you very much, gentlemen. I
merci beaucoup messieurs je vous
wish you a very good day.
souhaite une très bonne journée un
[Music]
[Musique]
PL. From the moment we allow
PL à partir du moment où on autorise les
operators to do what they want on
opérateurs à faire ce qu'ils veulent sur
the network, we are in fact allowing them to
le réseau en fait on les autorise à
modify society, allowing them to
modifier la société on les autorise à
modify the way people
modifier la façon dont les gens
interact. Better and better, there are more and more
interagissent de mieux en mieux o il y a
opportunities, more and
de plus en plus d'opportunités de plus
more knowledge and talent, more and more
en plus de savoir et de talent et de
solutions, and more and
plus en plus de solutions et de plus en
more capital. That's for projects. What's currently
plus de capitaux voilà pour des projets
lacking is that
c'estàdire que ce qui manque à l'heure
in many countries,
actuelle que dans beaucoup de pays on
the institutional framework is evolving
fait évoluer le cadre institutionnel
to include civil society in the
pour inclure la société civile dans le
debate, and we are very far from doing that in
débat et on est très loin de faire ça en
France. I think it's even a bit of a
France je pense c'est même un peu la
terror for institutions.
terreur des institutions